CONTACT INFORMATION Rm 614, Kelvin Building University of Glasgow Glasgow, G12 8QQ United Kingdom Work: +44 (0)14133 08855 Web: www.pauljwright.co.uk Email: paul.wright@glasgow.ac.uk Publication List: SAO/NASA ADS

RESEARCH INTERESTS My interests range from stellar to solar physics; my main interests lie in the heating of the solar atmosphere, including active regions and loops. I have expertise in analysis of data from SDO/AIA, Hinode/EIS, Hinode/XRT, and NuSTAR Solar observations.

**EDUCATION** 

### University of Glasgow, Glasgow, UK

2014 – present (expected 2018)

Ph.D. Solar Physics

Thesis Topic: *The Energetics of Small Flares and Brightenings* Advisers: Dr Iain G. Hannah, Dr Alexander MacKinnon

### University of Southampton, Southampton, UK

2010 - 2014

MPhys Astrophysics with a year abroad

First class honours (1:1) Adviser: Professor Malcolm Coe

### Harvard University/Harvard-Smithsonian CfA, Cambridge, MA

2013 - 2014

MPhys Astrophysics with a year abroad

Thesis Topic: Superflare Rates of Solar-Like Stars Advisers: Dr Steven H. Saar, Dr Jeremy J. Drake

CURRENT ACADEMIC APPOINTMENT

# **Affiliate Staff Member**, University of Glasgow SUPA School of Physics and Astronomy

2017 – present

 Investigating the non-flaring coronal time-series data for signs of the coronal heating mechanism.

PREVIOUS
ACADEMIC
APPOINTMENTS

#### Post-Graduate Research Assistant, University of Glasgow

2014 - 2017

SUPA School of Physics and Astronomy

Project: The Energetics of Small Flares and Brightenings

- Analysed observations of the Sun with *NuSTAR*, a telescope not designed for heliophysics. These observations are the most sensitive of their kind and have resulted in numerous, wide-ranging highly-collaborative peer-reviewed publications.
- Analysed non-flaring coronal time-series in order to extract signatures of the coronal heating mechanism. Techniques included Fourier analysis, Wavelet analysis, and Local Intermittency Measure.
- Studied the temperature distribution of the solar atmosphere through the recovery of an ill-posed inverse problem (the differential emission measure, DEM) using techniques such as Tikhonov Regularization, Markov-Chain Monte Carlo, and Sparsity.
- This work had coverage by news outlets including The BBC...

Collaborators: Iain Hannah, Alexander MacKinnon

### Visiting Researcher, NASA Goddard Space Flight Center (GSFC)

2016

Heliophysics Science Division

• Worked on the possibility of implementing DEM maps in the Helioviewer project, and their usefulness as an input for various established analysis techniques.

Collaborators: Nicholeen Viall, Jack Ireland

# **Research Scholar**, Harvard-Smithsonian Center for Astrophysics (CfA) 2013 – 2014 Solar and Stellar X-Ray Group

- Designed and implemented a sophisticated stellar flare detection routine for long-cadence (30 mins) *Kepler* data.
- This work has had coverage by Science, and The Smithsonian Magazine.

Collaborators: Steven Saar, Søren Meibom, Jeremy Drake, Vinay Kashyap

REFEREED JOURNAL PUBLICATIONS	[1] Marsh, A. J., Smith, D. M., Glesener, L. et al 2017. First NuSTAR Limits on Quiet Sun Hard X-Ray Transient Events, ApJ (in revision)		
	[2] Wang, J., Simões, P. J. A., Jeffrey, N. L. S. et al 2017. Observations of Reconnection Flows in a Flare on The Solar Disk, ApJL, 847, L1		
	[3] <b>Wright, P. J.</b> , Hannah, I. G., Grefenstette, B. W., et al 2017. Microflare Heating of a Solar Active Region Observed with NuSTAR, Hinode/XRT, and SDO/AIA, ApJ, 844, 132		
	[4] Kuhar, M., Krucker, S., Hannah, I. G., et al 2017. Evidence of Significant Input in the Late Phase of a Solar Flare from NuSTAR X-ray Observation 835, 6		
FIRST AUTHOR PUBLICATIONS IN PREPERATION	[5] Wright, P. J., Hannah, I. G., Viall, N. M., et al		
	[6] Wright, P. J., Saar, S. H., Meibom, S., et al		
Conferences,	Invited Oral Presentations		
WORKSHOPS, &	ISSI Team Meeting: Coronal Nanoflares, Bern, CH	2016	
SCHOOLS	Harvard-Smithsonian Center for Astrophysics, Cambridge, MA, USA	2014	
SCHOOLS		2014	
	Oral/ePoster Presentations		
	Solar Physics Division Meeting (SPD/AAS), Portland, OR, USA	2017	
	Coronal Loops Workshop VIII, Palermo, Sicily, IT	2017	
	Living with a Star (SDO/LWS) Workshop, Burlington, VT, USA	2016	
	Hinode 10, Nagoya, JP	2016	
	National Astronomy Meeting 2016, Nottingham, UK	2016	
	Hinode 9, Belfast, UK	2015	
	Glasgow-Cambridge Flare Workshop, Glasgow, UK	2015	
	Poster Presentations		
	European Solar Physics Meeting (ESPM), Budapest, HU	2017	
	Solar Physics Division Meeting (SPD/AAS), Portland, OR, USA	2017	
	Living with a Star (SDO/LWS) Workshop, Burlington, VT, USA	2016	
	Coronal Loops Workshop VII, Cambridge, UK	2015	
	NAM 2015, Llandudno, UK	2015	
	223rd AAS Meeting, National Harbor, MD, USA	2013	
		2011	
	Schools Attended		
	CESRA Radio Summer School 2015, Glasgow, UK	2015	
	STFC Advanced Summer School in Solar Physics, Dundee, UK	2014	
	Conferences/Workshops Attended		
	NuSTAR Heliophysics Workshop (remote participation), Berkeley, CA, USA	2017	
	SUPA Cormack Astronomy Meeting, Edinburgh, UK	2015	
	RAS Discussion Meeting: Results from IRIS, London, UK	2015	
	SUPA Cormack Astronomy Meeting, Edinburgh, UK	2014	
	1st Space Glasgow Research Conference, Glasgow, UK	2014	
AWARDS AND	SUPA School of Physics and Astronomy, University of Glasgow		
GRANTS TOTAL: £7000	Solar Physics Division Meeting (SPD/AAS) Student Poster Award	2017	
	Solar Physics Division Meeting (SPD/AAS) Studentship Award	2017	
	Coronal Loops Workshop VIII Travel Award	2017	
	National Astronomical Observatory of Japan Travel Award	2016	
	Hinode 9 Travel Award	2015	
	European Space Agency/Cambridge Philosophical Society Travel Award	2015	

AWARDS AND GRANTS (CONT.)	School of Physics and Astronomy, University of Southampton Research Scholarship Summer Studentship Grant	2013 2013
TEACHING	University of Glasgow Astronomy 1 Tutorial Demonstrator Supervised students, and marked first year astronomy problem sets	2016 - 2017
	Physics Pre-University Summer School  Engaged students in various physics experiments and marked assig	2015 nments.
	Astronomy 3/4 (Honours) Laboratory Demonstrator  Demonstrated, supervised, and marked a number of final-year researching topics such as asteroid light curves, and solar limb darkening	
MEMBERSHIPS	NuSTAR Heliophysics Working Group, Member International Space Science Institute (ISSI), Young Scientist Member Member of Paola Testa's ISSI Team: New Diagnostics of Particle Acce Coronal Nanoflares from Chromospheric Observations and Modeling Royal Astronomical Society, RAS Fellow	2015 – present 2015 – present leration in Solar 2014 – present
COMMUNITY INVOLVEMENT	Nature Communications, Reviewer CESRA Radio Summer School, Volunteer Organiser	2017 – present 2015
SCIENTIFIC OUTREACH	Glasgow Science Centre, Demonstrator British Science Week, Demonstrator Institute of Physics: Women and Girls in Science, Demonstrator Scottish Television (STV), Guest Presenter World Wide Telescope, Ambassador BBC Stargazing Live, Demonstrator So'ton Astrodome, Demonstrator BBC Bang Goes The Theory Roadshow, Demonstrator	2016 2016 2016 2015 2013 – 2014 2013 2012 2012
	UK Solar Physics (UKSP) Nuggets, concise, easy-to-read science articles 84. The first NuSTAR microflare	2017
	Hinode/XRT Picture of the Week (XPOW) The First Microflare Observations with Hinode/XRT & NuSTAR	2017
PERSONAL PROJECTS	ColourBlind, A repository for colour-blind-friendly colour tables.	Citations: 1
PROFESSIONAL DEVELOPMENT	Coursera, Inc. (MOOC Platform) Using Coursera.org, a massive open online course (MOOC) platform, to take specializations (a series of related courses and a final capstone project) offered by accredited universities to further develop skills and understanding in a wide range of computer science applications.	
	<ul> <li>Data Science, Johns Hopkins University Nine-course (plus capstone) introduction to data science.</li> <li>Mastering Software Development in R, Johns Hopkins University Four-course (plus capstone) specialization providing riguourous t language.</li> </ul>	2017 – present 2017 – present raining in the R
	Statistics with R, Duke University Four-course (plus capstone) specialization providing further traini guage with emphasis on statistics.	2017 – present ng in the R lan-

PROFESSIONAL
DEVELOPMENT
(CONT.)

#### Big Data, UC San Diego

2017 – present

Five-course (plus capstone) introduction to big data using Hadoop with MapReduce, Spark, Pig and Hive.

# Machine Learning, University of Washington

2017 - present

Three-course (plus capstone) introduction to Machine Learning.

### Graphic Design, CalArts

2017 - present

Four-course (plus capstone) introduction the fundamental skills required to make sophisticated graphic design.

### edx, Inc. (MOOC Platform)

Introduction to Computer Science (CS50x), Harvard University 2017 – present An introduction to the intellectual enterprises of computer science and the art of programming including languages such as C, and SQL.

# TECHNICAL SKILLS:

Computing: C, Python, R (caret, ggplot2, knitr), SQL, CRAN, IDL, LTEX, git, GitHub, Hadoop (MapReduce, Spark, Pig, Hive), Linux/Unix, Mac OSX, Microsoft Windows, Bash, Microsoft Office, Adobe Creative Cloud, Keynote, Wordpress, Shiny, GoogleVis, and Plotly, HTML, CSS, Javascript

*General:* Data Analysis, Data Visualization, Interdisciplinary Collaboration, Public Speaking, Statistics, Teaching, Writing (Technical & Lay)

## MORE Information

More information and auxiliary documents can be found at http://www.pauljwright.co.uk, on ResearchGate, and GitHub.